-==www.RagBear.com==-
是, 首相  第1季第7集
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
翻译: tanya312
校对: tpring
时间轴: T-boy
主教之争
对菲奥娜麦格的关注持续增加
Growing concern for Fiona McGregor,
这名英国护士在海湾国家库朗
the nurse held in the Gulf state of Kumran
因持有一瓶威士忌被捕
for alleged possession of a bottle of whisky.
被判10年徒刑和40下鞭刑
Her sentence of 10 years' imprisonment
即将确认执行
and 40 lashes is awaiting confirmation.
今天 她母亲偕同当地议员斯图尔特戈登
Today, her mother, accompanied by her MP, Stuart Gordon,
和其他支持者
and a group of sympathisers,
对库朗大使馆提交请愿书
took a petition to the Kumran embassy,
但库朗拒绝接受
but the Kumrani's refused to accept it.
外交大臣对此事表示遗憾
The Foreign Secretary described the incident as regrettable,
但并未计划采取行动
but no action is planned.
关掉吧 伯纳
Turn it off, Bernard.
今日英镑汇率仍然不妙
The Pound has a bad day
真让人忧心 汉弗莱 公众同情情绪很强
This is very worrying. There's a lot of public sympathy.
我肯定外交大臣会给您建议的
I'm sure the Foreign Secretary will advise you.
他建议我袖手旁观
He advises me to do nothing.
我肯定这是个好建议
I'm sure that's good advice.
如果袖手旁观 我们会显得既无情 又无能
If we do nothing, we look heartless. And feeble.
政府不可以同时
It doesn't do the government any good to
显得既无情又无能
look heartless and feeble simultaneously.
你说呢 伯纳?
What do you think, Bernard?
不如想点办法
Perhaps you could arrange it
让您显得要么无情 要么无能?
so you only look heartless and feeble alternately.
汉弗莱 我们得采取措施
Humphrey, we must do something.
首相 库朗是英国的好朋友
Prime Minister, The Kumranis are good friends of Britain.
在我国下大笔国防订单
They just placed a huge defence contract with us,
向我们通报苏联在伊拉克的动向
they tell us about the Soviets in Iraq,
甚至为我们破坏石油输出国组织协定
they even sabotage OPEC agreements for us.
我们惹不起他们
We can't afford to upset them.
我都知道 汉弗莱
I know, Humphrey,
可一个英国国民要受酷刑了
but a British national is facing a barbaric punishment
为在国外犯的一点小过失
for a trivial offence committed in a foreign country.
外交部是保卫英国国民利益的
The Foreign Office is there to protect British nationals.
是保卫英国国家利益的
They are there to protect British interests.
挨鞭子可不符合她的利益
It's not in her interest to be flogged.
救她也不符合我们的利益
It's not in ours to prevent it.
符合 这可能重创政府威信
This could hurt the government very badly.
据我所知 明天外交大臣
Well, I understand that tomorrow the Foreign Secretary will
将发出照会 严正抗议
deliver a strong note of protest to The Kumranis.
干嘛不现在发?
Why can't he do it now?
还没征求库朗同意呢
We haven't got their agreement yet.
我们正在秘会大使
We're seeing the ambassador privately now.
一旦他们接受了措辞 我们就发
Once they approve the wording, we hand it over.
然后我们就仁至义尽了      真无情
Then we'll have done all we can.        Very heartless.
无情总比无脑好
It's safer to be heartless than mindless.
历史就是无情对无脑的胜利史
History is the triumph of the heartless over the mindless.
外交部休想让内阁同意这种政策
The Cabinet will never agree to this policy.
外交部从未指望内阁同意他们任何政策
The F.O. never expect that for their policies.
所以他们从不解释清楚
That's why they never fully explain them.
甚至对外交大臣?
Even to the Foreign Secretary?
尤其对外交大臣
Especially not to the Foreign Secretary.
外交部只要求他们实施后
All that the Foreign Office requires is that the Cabinet
内阁同意就行
agree to their decisionsonce once they've been taken.
还有事吗 首相? 我约了人吃晚餐
Will that be all? Prime Minister,I have a dinner engagement.
好 没事了      首相
Yes, I suppose so.        Prime Minister
今晚的招待会要开始了
It's time to get ready for the reception here this evening.
谁要来?      英国圣公会代表
Oh, who's coming?        The synod of the Church of England.
圣埃德蒙教区主教出缺了
There's a vacancy in Bury St Edmunds.
每当重要主教出缺 他们就要来      为什么?
They come here when a bishopric is vacant.        Why?
游说 有两个候选人 免得您选错
To lobby. So you don't choose the wrong name.
我怎么知道该选谁?
How should I know which one to choose?
像其他公务员决定一样 首相
It's like any Civil Service option.Prime Minister
这是个纸牌戏法
It will be a conjuring trick.
随便抽张牌 总抽中
You know. Take any card, you always end up with
魔术师要您抽的那张
the card the magician forced you to take.
要是我不抽呢?      您会抽的
Suppose I don't take it?        You will.
都给我哪些牌?
Who are these cards I am supposed to choose?
教会的牌
Well, With the Church,
不外乎是J(恶棍)或者Q(同性恋)
you usually get the choice of a knave or a queen.
我们都很欢迎你回贝利参加晚宴
We do appreciate you dining at the college.
与老朋友吃饭向来是我的荣幸
It is always a pleasure to dine with old friends.
谢谢 院长
Thank you, Master.
汉弗莱 我还有四五年就退休了
Humphrey, I'll be retiring in four or five years.
你不也是吗?
Isn't that roughly when you retire from the civil service?
对
Yes.
司库和我都觉得 你就是
The Bursar and I think you could be just the chap
继任贝利学院院长的合适人选
to succeed me as Master of Ballie.
真的?
Really?
但还有一个障碍 教务长
But there is one obstacle. The Dean.
他有什么意见?
Why is he an obstacle?
他说你聪明过头了
He says you're too clever by half.
我还以为在牛津
I should have thought that at Oxford
说人聪明是赞誉呢
to be called clever might be rather a compliment.
他还说你自鸣得意      多谢了 司库
He also says you're smug.        Thank you, Bursar.
你有得是资本嘛
Well, you've got a lot to be smug about.
要是我也一年挣7万5
If I had 75,000 a year,
有爵位 有物价指数化养老金
a knighthood, an index-linked pension,
还有群政客专替我背黑锅
and a bunch of politicians to take the blame for
我也会得意的
all my mistakes, I'd be pretty smug myself!
教务长生怕
The Dean is paranoid that
我们在背着他密谋此事
we're intriguing in this matter behind his back.
所以我们决定...
That is why we decided to...
趁他不在时跟你谈
discuss it with you while he's away.
对 当然
Yes Quite.
要让你当贝利院长
The only way you'll become Master of Baillie
唯一办法是甩掉教务长
is if we can dump the Dean.
怎么甩?      不好办 他是个懒鬼
But how?        It isn't easy. He's a lazy devil.
一周只用工作4小时
He only has to do four hours' work a week.
上一堂课 几次辅导
Give one lecture and a couple of tutorials
就享有终身教职
and he's got tenure for life!
他只有两样爱好 板球和蒸汽机
Only two interests - cricket and steam engines.
从不读一本新书 从没有一个新想法
Never reads a new book, never thinks a new thought.
所以在牛津教书最合适不过了
So being an Oxford don is the perfect job.
那什么才能把他调离贝利呢?
So what would get him away from Baillie?
唯有主教职位      主教职位?
Only a bishopric.        A bishopric?
我们在考虑圣埃德蒙
We wondered about Bury St Edmunds.
正好出缺了 是吗?
That's up for grabs, isn't it?
对 非常不错的教区 在上院占一席
Yes, a very agreeable diocese. It has a seat in the Lords.
教务长一定喜欢
The Dean would like that.
他第三大爱好是往贵族阶层爬
His third hobby is sucking up to the aristocracy.
那当然 不过 这不由我作主
Naturally. Well, it's not up to me at all.
教会想保持平衡
The Church wants to maintain the balance.
平衡什么?
What balance?
信上帝和不信上帝的成员
Between those who believe in God and those who don't.
教会还有不信上帝的成员?
Is there anyone in the Church who doesn't?
有啊 大多数主教
Oh, yes. Most of the bishops.
无论如何 圣埃德蒙已经有主了
But, in any case, Bury St Edmunds is all sewn up.
归史丹弗教士
Canon Stanford is getting the job.
我们以为要由首相选呢
We thought the Prime Minister had to choose.
对 可他们另一个候选人没指望
But they gave an impossible second candidate.
再说
In any case,
教务长的公职资历不足
the Dean hasn't done enough public service to qualify.
还有哪个教区出缺吗?
Are any other dioceses coming free?
唉 这种事不常有
Well, it doesn't happen very often.
年纪大的都不必60岁退休
The older appointees don't have to retire at 60.
主教通常很长寿
Bishops tend to have long lives.
显然上帝不急着召他们去陪他
Apparently the Lord isn't all that keen for them to join Him
你觉得教务长需要哪种公职资历?
What sort of public service did you have in mind for the Dean
何不让主教派他去库朗
Well, why don't you get the bishop to send him to Kumran,
去为那个护士说情呢?
to try to intercede on behalf of that nurse?
阿拉伯人喜欢他 他是伊斯兰教专家
The Arabs love him because he's an expert in Islamic studies
他也喜欢阿拉伯人 横竖我们不吃亏
He'd love the Arabs. Either way, we can't lose.
对呀
That's right.
如果他失败 他尽力了
If he fails, at least he's tried.
如果他成功 他就是英雄
If he succeeds, he's a hero.
如果他回不来 也没人想念他
And if he doesn't come back, he won't be missed.
多可怕的国家啊
No, it's such an awful country.
偷东西要砍手
They cut people's hands off and
女人一通奸 就要被砸死
women get stoned when they commit adultery.
不像英国
Unlike Britain where
她们喝到醉死 然后去通奸
they commit adultery when they get stoned
他可能丢几个零件再回来呢
He may even come back with a few parts missing!
瞧 手没了
Look, no hands!
抱歉犹豫这么久 彼得
Sorry to be so hesitant, Peter.
我从没委任过主教
I've never appointed a bishop before.
是向女王推荐委任 首相
recommended the appointment to the sovereign, PM
对 给我讲讲史丹弗教士
Yes. Tell me about Canon Stanford.
好的 麦克名望很高 他是个现代派
Well, Mike is very highly thought of. He's a modernist.
现代派?      神学术语 首相
Modernist?        A theological term. Prime Minister
他似乎认为
It seems that he accepts that
圣经里某些事不能照字面理解
some events described in the Bible are not literally true.
他认为那些是比喻 神话或传奇故事
He sees them as metaphors, myths or legends.
他只关注它们的精神或哲学涵义
He's interested in their spiritual and philosophical truth.
你是说他不信七日创世
He doesn't believe the world was made in seven days
夏娃是亚当肋骨这一套?
and Eve came out of Adam's rib?
正是 首相      貌似挺明智的 还有呢?
Precisely.        Sounds very sensible. Anything else?
他上过温彻斯特和牛津新学院
He went to Winchester and New College, Oxford,
他是首选
and his name is first on the list.
好像不错      他夫人也极其合适
Sounds good.        And he has an eminently suitable wife.
你是说她虔诚 广做善事?
Devout, full of good works?
不 我是说她是奇切斯特伯爵的女儿
No, I mean she's the daughter of the Earl of Chichester.
明白了 第二位呢?
I see. And what about the second?
第二位是保罗哈维博士
Well, second is Doctor Paul Harvey.
怎样?
And?
他是个可敬的人      然而?
He's an admirable man.        But?
当然 您来拿主意 首相
It's your choice, of course, Prime Minister
可人们怀疑
but there's a suspicion
他倾向于政教分离主义
he tends towards disestablishmentarianism.
什么?
What?
认为圣公会
The view that the Church of England
不该成为国家政权的一部分
shouldn't be part of the state.
有些人觉得该把它们分离出去
Some people feel it should be separate,
像卫理公会和天主教会一样
like Methodists or Catholics.
他们说老百姓觉得国教只是
They think ordinary people feel the established church is
统治阶级的俱乐部,而不是信仰
a club for the ruling classes. Not a faith
听起来人不错啊
Sounds a good man.
当然 完全由您做主 首相
Well, it's entirely up to you, of course, Prime Minister,
不过我怀疑女王陛下会有点意外
but I suspect Her Majesty might be a little surprised
如果您要她任命
if you asked her to appoint a man who'd
一个让她打破加冕时"捍卫国教"誓言的人
make her break her coronation vows to defend the Church
那干吗把他列进来?
Why's he on the list, then?
他也不完全是政教分离派
Well, he's not quite a disestablishmentarian yet.
可他的思想似乎有这个趋向
But that's the way his mind seems to be moving.
明白了
I see.
所以我得选麦克史丹弗或麦克史丹弗?
So I'm being asked to choose Mike Stanford or Mike Stanford?
首相 委员会已经
Prime Minister, The Commission is offering you
提名了两个候选人
the two names which emerged
自由选举出来的?
Was there an open election?
不可能 主教遵从使徒递袭
No. Bishops are in the apostolic succession.
什么意思?      上帝的旨意
What's that?        It's God's will.
当初犹大堕落之后 就要换人
When Judas Iscariot blotted his copybook, he was replaced.
他们让圣灵决定
They let the Holy Ghost decide.
圣灵怎么传达旨意?      抓阄
How did he make his views known?        By drawing lots.
这次不能让圣灵决定吗?
Couldn't we let the Holy Ghost decide this time?
没人相信圣灵知道
No one's confident the Holy Ghost would know
英国圣公会主教的条件
what makes a good Church of England bishop.
汉弗莱爵士快到了 首相 能明天再谈吗?
Sir Humphrey is due here now. Could we continue tomorrow?
没问题 谢谢 首相
Not at all. Thank you, Prime Minister.
首相 任命史丹弗
Prime Minister, appointing Canon Stanford
可能会自摆乌龙
may be an own goal
我去调他的履历好吗?
May I get his career details?
好 谢谢      我叫汉弗莱爵士进来
Yes, please do.        And I'll send Sir Humphrey in.
伯纳 首相      汉弗莱 要雪利酒吗?
Bernard. Prime Minister.        Ah, Humphrey. Sherry?
好的 谢谢
Yes, thank you.
汉弗莱 圣公会的现代派是什么意思?
What's a modernist in the Church of England?
这个嘛 "现代派"指不信教的人
Ah, well, the word ''modernist'' is code for non-believer.
你说无神论者?      不不 首相
You mean an atheist?        No, no.Prime Minister
无神论者拿不到教会津贴
An atheist couldn't continue to draw his stipend,
所以当他们不信上帝了
so when they stop believing in God
就自称现代派
they call themselves modernists.
圣公会怎能
How could the Church of England
推荐无神论者当主教?
suggest an atheist as bishop
很简单
They are easy.
圣公会主要是个社会团体
The Church of England is primarily a social organisation,
不是宗教团体
not religious.
是吗?      对 我国多样社会结构的一部分
Is it?        Part of the rich social fabric of the country.
主教要谈吐得体 礼数周全
Bishops need to be the sort of chaps who speak properly,
懂得选用刀叉
know which knife and fork to use.
让人心生敬畏的人物
The sort of people one can look up to.
所以史丹弗教士的夫人特别合适
So Canon Stanford's wife's eminently suitable
当然 干杯
Of course. Cheers.
真没别的候选人了?      不能说有
Is there really no other candidate?        Well, not really.
近来有更好的职位出缺了
There were better jobs available recently.
什么比主教(象棋里的相)还好? 赌棍(车)
What's better than a bishop? A rook?
很好笑
Very droll.
不 温莎教长就是更好的职位
No, Dean of Windsor is a better job.
西敏寺教长也是
Or Westminster.
能使人和皇室亲密起来
It enables one to be on better terms with the Royals.
这么说主教就是个名份喽?
So being a bishop is just a matter of status?
能穿长袍 长统靴
Dressing up in cassocks and gaiters.
对 尽管长统靴只有
Yes, though gaiters are now only worn
在重大宗教场合才穿
at significant religious events
比如皇室游园会
like the Royal garden party.
为什么?      教会想尽量拉近联系
Why?        The Church is trying to be more relevant.
跟上帝?      不 当然不是 首相
To God?        No, of course not. PM.
社会学上的联系
I meant relevant in sociological terms.
那在教会看来
So the ideal candidate in the Church's view
最理想的莫过于一位社会主义社交名流?
is a cross between a socialite and a socialist?
正是
Precisely.
抱歉打扰一下
May I just interrupt.
您要听史丹弗教长的履历吗?
May I give you career details of Dean Conan Stanford?
请说吧
Please do.
神学院毕业后 任设菲尔德助理牧师
He was chaplain to the Bishop of Sheffield.
提拔为教区
He moved on to be the diocesan advisor
异教徒团体与社区顾问
on ethnic communities and social responsibility.
组织过各种不同信仰交流会
He organised conferences on inter-faith interface
基督徒和马克思主义者
and inter-faith between Christians and Marxists,and
基督徒和格林汉芒左派反战妇女营
between Christians and the women of Greenham Common
他曾任埃塞克斯大学牧师
He was chaplain at the University of Essex,
神学院副院长
vice-principal at a theological college
现任教会理事会
and is now secretary to the Disarmament Committee
裁军委员会干事
of the Council of Churches.
他当过普通教区牧师吗?
Has he ever been an ordinary vicar of a parish?
天啊 没有 首相
Good heavens, no. PM.
想当主教的神职人员
Clergymen who want to be bishops
总要回避教区工作
try to avoid pastoral work.
你是说 他是个政坛刺头?
So you're saying he's a political troublemaker?
不 不过他可能阻碍您处理社会问题
No, but he could be a thorn in your side on social issues
罢工 公共福利开支
strikes, public expenditure on welfare,
内城建设 就业 国防之类问题
inner cities, unemployment, defence.
有意思吧 如今
It's interesting that nowadays
政客们喜欢拿道德说事
politicians want to talk about moral issues
主教们却忙着谈政治
and bishops want to talk politics.
他还会拥有主教和
And he'd speak with the authority of a bishop
上院议员的话语权
and from the Lords.
他设计过南伦敦一座教堂
He designed a new church in South London
专门设有橙汁供应区
with places for dispensing orange juice,
家庭区 示威组织区
family planning and organising demos...
却没地方主持圣餐      你说真的?
But no place for Holy Communion.        Are you serious?
倒有一个两用厅
Well, there was a dual-purpose hall.
教会就批准啦?
And the Church approved this?
当然 教会由神学家管理      所以呢?
Of course. The Church is run by theologians.        So?
神学是把不可知论者
Well, theology is a device for enabling agnostics
留在教会内的手段
to stay within the Church.
我不想要史丹弗 我该怎么办?
I don't want Stanford. What am I to do?
您可以两个都拒绝
You could turn both candidates down,
可这就开了特例 我们不推荐
but that would be exceptional and not advised.
就算一个候选人想把上帝赶出教会
Even though one wants God out of the Church of England
另一个想赶走女王?
and the other wants the Queen out?
女王和教会不可分离
The Queen is inseparable from the Church.
上帝呢?
What about God?
我想他就是所谓"附加选项"
I think he's what's called an optional extra.
伯纳马上过来 那护士有消息吗?
Bernard's on his way up. Any more news about that nurse?
没 没什么消息
No, not really.
外交部没办法吗?
Can't the Foreign Office do something?
外交部不是想办法的
The Foreign Office is there to explain
是解释为什么没办法的
why things can't be done.
这可能严重损害政府
This could damage us very badly.
外交部只会耸耸肩
All the Foreign Office does is shrug
解释我们惹不起库朗人
and say we mustn't upset the Kumranis.
她一定很害怕      谁?
Must be ghastly for her.        Who?
哦 那个护士 对
Oh, that nurse. Yes.
你不比外交部在乎她      哦 安妮
You don't care about her either.        Oh, Annie.
你只在乎你的支持率
You're only worried about your popularity.
胡说
That's not true.
抱歉 首相 出了大事
Sorry, Prime Minister. It's rather important.
外交部来电话说
The Foreign Office just right to say
班伯里主教和教会传道会
The Bishop of Banbury and the Church Missionary Society
宣布他们派贝利学院教务长
are sending the Dean of Baillie College to
去库朗执行仁慈使命 拯救护士
Kumran on a mercy mission.
牛津的教师? 为什么?
An Oxford don? Why?
他是基督徒 也是伊斯兰教专家
He is a Christian. He's an expert on Islam.
这是教会跟教会碰头
It's a faith to faith meeting.
好 伯纳
All right. Bernard
告诉外交部我支持他们支持他
Tell the Foreign Office I support their moves to support him
不 外交部想请您阻止
No, the Foreign Office want you to stop it.
他们说这是无用功
They say it's a futile gesture
只会损害两国友好关系
which will impair our relationship with a friendly country.
我才不阻止呢 我觉得是好办法
I am not going to stop it. But I think it's a good idea.
对吧 安妮?
Don't you, Annie?
你是说可能救出护士?
You mean it might save the nurse?
对 也有这原因
Er, yes, that too.
首要目标 好 叫他们放手去做
Principally. All right, tell them to go ahead.
坎特伯雷大主教问您
Oh, Lambeth Palace want to know
圣埃德蒙的事定了没
if you've decided about Bury St Edmunds.
好的 伯纳 谢谢      晚安
All right, Bernard. Thank you.        Good night.
圣埃德蒙的什么事?
What's happening in Bury St Edmunds?
要我选个主教      真可笑
I've got to choose a bishop.        That's ridiculous!
为什么?      你不大信教吧 亲爱的
Why?        You're not exactly religious.
我是首相 宗教跟这无关
I'm Prime Minister. Religion has nothing to do with it.
跟主教无关?      基本无关
To do with bishops?        Not really.
他们就是经理 穿得花哨而已
They're just managers in fancy dress.
圣公会有17.2万亩地产
The Church of England has over 172,000 acres of land,
数千佃户
thousands of tenants,
租赁权 产权和投资
leaseholds, property and investments
总值达16亿镑
worth a total of 1.6 billion pounds.
理想的主教是个集团公司经理
The ideal bishop is a corporate executive.
兼任银行家
A sort of merchant banker,
人事主管和不动产经济人
personnel manager and estate agent.
我希望你选个笃信上帝的
I'd prefer you to choose a man of God.
他们推荐了一个
They offered me one of those,
不过他想把教会变成宗教运动
but he wants to turn the Church into a religious movement.
他们想塞给我一个现代派
They're trying to force a modernist.
左派还是无神论者?
Marxist or atheist?
都是 无神论者倒不要紧
Both. Doesn't matter about the atheist bit,
可左派就麻烦了
but being a Marxist could cause me a lot of trouble
他要在上院演讲的
once he's in the House of Lords.
不能否决他吗?      会显得像搞政治的
Can't you turn him down?        It would look political.
你说教会就是搞政治的嘛
You said the Church IS political.
可不能显出来
But it mustn't look it.
明白了
I see.
干嘛不用宗教原因排除他?
Why not turn him down on religious grounds?
怎么讲?
How do you mean?
他相信有天堂地狱吗?      当然不信
Does he believe in Heaven and Hell?        Of course not.
圣灵感孕呢? 神子复活呢?
The virgin birth? The resurrection?
不 这些都不信
No, nothing like that.
那还不够?      安妮 你太聪明了
Isn't that enough?        Annie, you're brilliant!
我要两个都否决 逼他们再提一个
I'll reject both candidates and force them to submit another
我想要的是大家都接受的人
I really want a candidate who'll get on with everybody.
对什么都没主意的?      对
Someone without strong views on anything?        Yes.
如果有基督教倾向也许更好
It might help if he were inclined towards Christianity.
反正没坏处
That wouldn't do any real harm.
那你真正需要的是个秘密基督徒
So what you need is a sort of closet Christian.
正是 谢谢 亲爱的
Exactly. Thank you, darling.
BBC晚间新闻
The Six 0'Clock News from the BBC,
苏罗雷和尼古拉威彻播出
with Sue Lawley and Nicholas Witchell.
晚上好
Good evening.
最新消息 经过在库朗两周的磋商
News is just coming in that after two weeks in Kumran
贝利学院教务长成功
the Dean of Baillie College has succeeded
释放了菲奥娜麦格
in obtaining the release of Fiona McGregor,
被捕下狱的英国护士
the British nurse held there in prison.
早先她因持有一瓶威士忌
She was awaiting a sentence of 40 lashes
被判40下鞭刑
for possessing a bottle of whisky.
她和教务长定于明天回国
She and the Dean are expected back in England tomorrow.
下面是其它新闻
Now for the rest of the news.
今日英镑汇率仍然不妙
The pound had another bad day...
是真的啊 真不敢相信
So it's true. I can't believe it.
灾难啊      灾难
It's a disaster.        Disaster!
谁的馊主意 派他去库朗的?
Whose idea was it to send him to Kumran?
这可难说 班伯里主教吧?
Eh, can't imagine. Bishop of Banbury perhaps?
外交部本来都控制局势了
We had the situation under control.
那还用说
Yes, of course you did.
我们提了抗议
We made our protest.
护士会悄悄挨鞭子
The nurse would have been quietly flogged and
塞到牢里去
stuffed in some jail.
不出几周 媒体就忘光了
Within a couple of weeks, the press would forget.
好在没什么实际损失
Still, no real damage done.
外交部损失重大啊
There is to the Foreign Office.
他们都快同意
We've almost got agreement to
我们在库朗设个监听站了
set up a signals listening post in Kumran.
我们说他们答应 我们就不纠缠护士的事
We said we wouldn't make a fuss if they signed.
这下最大的筹码没了
We've lost our best bargaining counter.
你们总可以再找个护士 栽瓶威士忌嘛
You could find another nurse and plant some Scotch on her!
这我们可办不到
I don't think we could do that.
对对 这样不好
No. No, it wouldn't be right.
不 风险太大了
No, it's too dangerous.
不过 至少帮我把她该死的母亲摆脱了
at least it's got that nurse's ghastly mother off my back
她一个劲写信 打电话 跟媒体
She's been writing and phoning and telling the press
说我们袖手旁观
that we haven't been doing anything.
真过分      媒体还都向着她
Extraordinary.        And the press have taken her part.
说什么我们不爱国      太过分了
Going on about being more patriotic!        Extraordinary.
他们说过外交部不少坏话
They've said a lot of unpleasant things,
可从没骂我们不爱国
but we've never been accused of patriotism!
有时我真难相信
Sometimes I can't believe the newspapers'
报界对外交局势这么无知
abject ignorance of diplomatic realities.
可我们对首相不好交待了
But we may have a problem with the PM now.
因为我们反对他派牧师?
Because we advised him against this?
还因为你让外交部长说
Because the Foreign Secretary said
释放她办不到
it was impossible to get her released!
我们没错 如果交给外交部
And we were right! If we'd left it to the Foreign Office
绝对办不到
it would have been impossible.
知道会怎样了吧
You see what will happen now?
媒体会说教会能力强过外交部
The press will say the Church succeeds where the F.O. fails.
又会翻出老一套
They'll dig out all the old cuttings
大使的豪华轿车
about ambassadors' Rolls Royces,
400万镑的大使馆
4 million embassies,
纳税人代缴的伊顿学费
school fees at Eton paid for by the taxpayer and
英国得到什么?
what does Britain get?
千万别 我有办法了      什么?
Don't. I know what we'll do.        What?
我们告诉媒体 是首相
We'll tell the press that it was the Prime Minister's
作主派教务长的
initiative to send the Dean.
好主意 首相就喜欢居功
Good idea. The PM will enjoy taking the credit.
首相不会因为这是撒谎 就不乐意吧?
There's no danger the PM will deny it because it isn't true?
绝对不会
None at all.
再向周日邮报透消息
And then for the Sundays
说是外交部建议首相的
we leak the idea that the Foreign Office suggested it to him
因为外交途径受阻了
when the diplomatic channels were blocked.
完美 这样没人有错
Perfect. Nobody gets the blame and
人人都有功
everybody gets the credit.
除了真想出这点子的人
Except the person who really thought it up.
我不介意
I don't mind.
我不介意他没功劳 不管是谁 抱歉
I don't mind that he doesn't get the credit. Excuse me.
喂 好 接过来
Hello? Oh, put him on.
你好 院长
Oh, hello, Master.
看到电视新闻了吗? 太棒了
Have you seen the television news? Splendid!
对 简直太棒了
Yes, absolutely splendid.
能推我们的朋友一把吧?
This could help our friend, eh?
绝对能
Certainly could.
什么时候有主教出缺?
How long until a bishopric falls vacant?
现在正是时候
Well, there's no time like the present.
我觉得圣埃德蒙之战还没完
I think the battle of Bury St Edmunds is not over yet.
对 我是说过 可又有新动向
I know what I said. There have been developments.
抱歉
Excuse me.
喂 好 请他进来 谢谢
Hello? Yes, ask him to come in. Thank you.
我看还有办法把教务长拉上起跑线
I think we can still get the Dean up to the starting gate.
后发制人 交给我就行了
As a late entry. Just leave it to me.
好的 再见 院长 再见
All right. Bye, Master. Bye-bye.
请进来 彼得
Ah, come in, Peter.
我听说皇室任命委员会
I understand there's a meeting of
明早要开会?
the Crown Appointments Commission in the morning?
对 他们知道了要选新的候选人
Yes, they are aware that a further candidate is required
因为首相觉得有必要打破传统
since the PM saw fit to break with tradition.
你是说 他非要选个信教的主教?
By insisting on a bishop who is a believer?
还有一个候选人 史蒂文萨默
There is one possible candidate, Steven Soames,
我们留了很多年了
but we've saved him up for years.
本打算派他去特鲁罗(英格兰西南)
We'd rather offer him Truro.
为什么?
Why?
特鲁罗...怎么说呢? 比较远
Well, Truro is... How shall I put it? Very remote.
对教会来说 等于斯旺西(威尔士)
It is to the Church what the Vehicle Licensing Centre
车牌管理处对公务员
in Swansea is to the Civil Service.
对啊
Yes.
萨默等了很多年了      好久不见
Soames has been waiting for years.        Long time, no see.
很好笑 汉弗莱
Oh, very droll, Humphrey.
对 他是有点讨厌
Yes, he is a bit of a nuisance.
老叫我们对上帝尽义务
He keeps on about our duty to God and that sort of things
我们想赶走他 "好久不见"
We rather wanted him out of the way. ''Long time, no see''!
对 可如果首相要信教的主教
Yes, but if the PM wants a religious bishop,
他是唯一候选人
he's the only candidate.
对 听起来不错 可有个问题
He sounds fine, but there is one little snag.
首相要两名新候选人      两名?
The PM wants you to put up two more names.        Two?
对 你得让首相觉得有选择余地
You must give the PM the feeling of a choice.
你得再找个候选人 貌似合理
You need a second candidate who is plausible,
但不可能的
but unacceptable.
我想不到 明早就开会了
I can't think who and the meeting's so soon.
贝利学院教务长不行吗?
Why not the Dean of Baillie College?
他确实不可能 但也不合理啊
I agree he is impossible, but not plausible.
怎么讲?
Why not?
他是个怪人
He's a crank!
极其自负 又无能得不像话
He's unbelievably vain and hopelessly incompetent.
对 可首相从不介意任命自负又无能的人
But the PM appoints people who are vain and incompetent
看看内阁
look at the Cabinet.
再说教务长刚刚大出风头
And the Dean's just had good publicity.
那他不是有选上的危险吗?
Isn't there a danger he'll get in?
一点也没有
Not the slightest.
首相说了要虔诚基督徒
The PM has stated that he wants a devout Christian.
教务长只相信伊斯兰教
The Dean only believes in Islam,
蒸汽机和板球俱乐部
steam engines and the MCC.
有次电视节目里
In fact, some smart aleck once asked him on TV
有人问他知不知道圣经是什么
if he knew what the Bible was.
他知道吗?
And did he?
对 他说那是基督教的古兰经
He said it's a Christian version of the Koran.
"吉姆的教务长鞭下拯救菲奥娜"
''Jim's Dean saves Fiona from lash''!
怎么样 汉弗莱?      精彩绝伦 首相
What about that?        Excellent.
"首相特使达成释放"
''Prime Minister's envoy secures release''.
精彩绝伦 首相
Excellent, Prime Minister.
"首相派出仁慈天使"      精彩绝伦 首相
''Angel of mercy was sent by PM''!        Excellent!
昨晚新闻把功劳全归给我 是我干的吧?
I was given full credit on the news. I suppose it was me.
铁板钉钉 报纸都说了
It must have been.
是我不让外交部制止他的
After all, I stopped the Foreign Office from stopping him,
一回事嘛
which is the same thing.
现在想改也晚了
Too late to change it now.
我还是不明白 外交部为什么归功于我
I wonder why they gave me the credit, though.
反正他们自己也占不了
Well, they couldn't take it themselves.
这样说起来像政府成就
This looks like a government achievement.
看 还有社论呢
There's even a leader.
"首相居功至伟
''It does the PM great credit that
正因为他未受外交锁链束缚"
he has not been bound by the shackles of diplomacy.
"库朗事件..." 这很重要的
''The Kumran aff...'' This is important.
对 可大主教在等您
Yes, but the Palace is waiting for your recommendation
提名圣埃德蒙主教
for Bury St Edmunds.
两个名字昨晚放您文件盒里了
The two names were in your box.
我觉得史蒂芬萨默貌似不错
I thought Steven Soames sounded right.
彼得也说不错 贝利教务长在库朗立了功
The Dean of Baillie did a very good job,
可我听说他是个怪人
but I gather he's rather eccentric.
我肯定萨默是
I'm sure that Soames is
皇家委员会希望您选的人
the choice the Commissioners are hoping you make.
怎么? 他有什么问题?
Oh? Why? What's wrong with him?
这个 我听说他是极端主义者
Well, I have heard say that he's an extremist.
你是说他信上帝?      极其虔诚 首相
You mean he believes in God?        He's very religious.
主教应该这样的吧?
That's all right for a bishop, isn't it?
他倾向于提出
He tends to raise issues
政府想回避的议题
that governments would prefer not to be raised.
他尖锐批判未成年人堕胎
He's a trenchant critic of abortion,
避孕 性教育 色情业
contraception under 16, sex education, pornography,
周日商业行为 便利离婚和银幕脏话
Sunday trading, easy divorce and bad language on TV.
他很可能挑战所有这些政策
He'd be likely to challenge government policy.
可这些议题
But these are subjects on which
政府不想出台政策
the government is hoping to have no policy.
我们的政策就是无政策
Our policy is not to have a policy.
没错 他就是反对您的无政策政策
Well, quite. He's against your no-policy policy.
他会要求您禁止堕胎 禁止周日交易...
He will demand that you ban abortion, Sunday trading...
谢谢 伯纳 我明白了
Thank you. I get the picture.
他还反对非洲的剥削与压迫
He's also against oppression in Africa.
我们也反对
So are we.
对 可不光白人政府 黑人政府他也反对
But he's against it from black AND white governments.
哦 你说他是种族主义者?
Oh. You mean he's a racist?
可您想选他也可以选
But you can choose him if you like.
我不能再否决两个候选人
I can't turn down another two names.
总还有贝利教务长嘛
Well, there is always the Dean of Baillie.
他不能真算数吧?
He's not really up to it, is he?
我听说他又懒又自负 还对基督教不感兴趣
I gather he's lazy, vain and uninterested in Christianity.
可他也不反对啊
But he's not against it!
我觉得他会是完美的英国主教
I think he would make a thoroughly suitable British bishop.
喜欢板球 蒸汽机
Cricket, steam engines and
对神学一无所知
a complete ignorance of theology.
他从没任过教职 一辈子待在牛津
He's never had an ordinary church job. He's been at Oxford.
可他在库朗干的不错      对
But he did well in Kumran.        Yes.
我今早听说 他想告诉媒体
I gather he's thinking of telling the press
库朗之行不是您的主意
that the Kumran visit wasn't your idea.
什么?      他想告诉媒体...
What?        He's thinking of telling the press...
对对 我听见了 他不能这么说
Yes, yes, I heard what you said. He can't say that!
我听说他有班伯里主教的信
I gather he has a letter from the Bishop of Banbury
在您介入前发出的
dated before your involvement.
可那就太丢人了
But that would be frightfully embarrassing!
好像我硬揽别人的功似的
Taking credit for something I didn't do.
对 我能预见头条
Yes, I can see the headlines now.
"教务长仁慈使命首相居功"
''PM takes credit for Dean's mercy mission''.
"吉姆没能搞定" 抱歉
''Jim didn't fix it!'' Sorry.
得制止他 怎么才能制止他?
He must be stopped! How can we stop him?
首相 据说他嫌认可不够...
He feels he hasn't had enough recognition...
教会在库朗一事中
That the Church hasn't had enough recognition
得到的认可不够
for its role in Kumran.
那就给他啊
Well, give him some.
今晚请他来喝酒 让媒体拍照
Get him round for drinks. Photo opportunity for the press.
这也许不大合适      为什么?
That might be a little improper.        Why?
您在考虑两个候选人
If you're considering two candidates,
总不能只请一个来喝酒吧
you can hardly invite just one round for a drink.
明白了      除非 当然...
I see.        Unless, of course...
如果您已经任命了他
If you'd already given him the job,
那就非常恰当了
then it would be perfectly proper.
说实话 汉弗莱
Actually, Humphrey,
我觉得贝利教务长当主教不错
I think he's rather a good choice for bishop.
真的 他这人有魄力      魄力
He's an enterprising chap.        Enterprising.
古怪也可以是优点
Eccentricity can be a virtue
改叫它个性的话
If you call it individualism.
这就是所谓不规则动词吧 "某人思想独立
It is called the irregular verb. I have an independent mind,
某人古怪 某人脑子有病"
you are an eccentric, he is round the twist.
抱歉
Sorry.
谢谢 伯纳
Thank you, Bernard.
再说 上院需要他这样的人
Furthermore, we need people like him in the House of Lords.
懂得阿拉伯世界
People who really understand the Arab world.
还有蒸汽机
And steam engines.
对 经过慎重考虑
Yes, on mature consideration,
我决定选贝利教务长
I think the Dean of Baillie is my choice.
通报大主教 伯纳
Convey that to the Palace, Bernard.
是 首相
Yes, Prime Minister.
马上 赶快 让媒体中午发布
Now! Fast. Announce it by midday.
让他6点来喝酒 快去
Get him round for a drinkie at six. Move!
依我之见 明智的决定 首相
A wise decision, if I may say so. PM
没错 汉弗莱
You may, Humphrey.
你怎么这么了解贝利教务长?
How come you know so much about the Dean of Baillie?
你不是贝利毕业的吗?
Weren't you at Baillie yourself?
没错 我是      替老朋友办事吧?
I was, yes.        Jobs for the boys, is it?
恰恰相反 首相 我们都算不上认识
On the contrary! I hardly know him.
说实话 我刚好知道他不喜欢我
In fact, I happen to know that he dislikes me.
您可以今晚亲自问他
You can ask him yourself this evening.
我也不太喜欢他
I don't like him very much, either.
真的?      以荣誉担保
Honestly?        On my word of honour.
你真无利可图?      怎么会有呢?
You have nothing to gain?        How could I have?
要这么说 干得好
In that case, well done.
有益而无私的建议
Helpful, impartial advice.
公务员系统最优良的传统
The best traditions of the Civil Service.
是 首相
Yes, Prime Minister.
破烂熊字幕组-==www.RagBear.com==-